Guide to the John Pintard Papers 1750-1925 (bulk 1770-1890) MS 490
New-York Historical Society
John Pintard Papers
1750-1925 (bulk 1770-1890)
New-York Historical Society
MS 490
6.8 Linear feet
John Pintard was a prominent New York City merchant who helped found the New-York Historical Society in 1804. He contributed significantly to numerous civic, cultural, religious, and philanthropic groups in New York. Pintard's Journal of Studies, 1797-1804, is digitized and available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
Biographical/Historical Note
John Pintard was born in New York City May 18, 1759, son of John and Mary (Cannon) Pintard. Both his parents died within a year of his birth, and Pintard was brought up by his paternal uncle, Lewis Pintard (1732-1818), a New York merchant. Under the guidance of his uncle, John Pintard attended the classical school of Hempstead, Long Island, and entered the College of New Jersey (Princeton University) in the class of 1776. During the American Revolution he served as Assistant Agent for American Prisoners, under his uncle Lewis, and at the close of the war, joined Lewis's mercantile business. On November 12, 1784, he married a distant cousin, Elizabeth Brasher (1765-1838).
Pintard became established in New York City as its business revived after the Revolution, and by the time it became the capital of the United States under the new Constitution, he was active in the mercantile, social, and cultural life of the city. On May 10, 1787, he was appointed secretary of the Mutual Assurance Company for Insuring Houses from Loss by Fire in New York, until his resignation on February 14, 1792. He was elected an Assistant Alderman of the East (Second) Ward of the city, September 29, 1789, and was re-elected, serving actively until March 12, 1792. He represented New York in the 14th session of the State Assembly, January-March, 1791, held in New York City. In November, 1790, he was appointed by New Jersey one of five commissioners to erect bridges over the Hackensack and Passaic Rivers. In 1790 and 1791, he was secretary of the New-York Manufacturing Society.
Pintard's progress was halted by his disastrous financial involvement in the failure of William Duer (1747-1799), who became insolvent and was imprisoned for debt in 1792. Duer's economic ties were so wide in the area that his financial collapse set off the first financial panic in New York City. Pintard surrendered everything he possessed, but because of some unsatisfied creditors, was arrested and confined for debt in the Newark prison from July 15, 1797, until August 6, 1798. In September, 1800, John Pintard took advantage of the federal "Act to establish an uniform system of bankruptcy throughout the United States," approved April 4, 1800. Pintard made an extended visit to New Orleans in 1801, and his favorable letters about the city to Secretary of State Albert Gallatin influenced President Thomas Jefferson in his decision to purchase the Louisiana Territory.
Though never reaching his former level of wealth, John Pintard firmly re-established himself in New York City. In March, 1804, he was appointed New York City Inspector, and in May, 1807, Clerk to the Common Council of the City. In that year he was elected secretary of the Mutual Insurance Company, successor of the Mutual Assurance Company of which he had been secretary 1787-1792, and which became later in the century the Knickerbocker Fire Insurance Company. That salaried position was Pintard's chief source of income during the next twenty years, until his retirement in 1829.
John Pintard was one of the earliest and staunchest advocates for the preservation and study of the history of New York and the United States. Pintard began to work towards the establishment of a historical society in the city in early 1804, and he was the leader in the organization of the New-York Historical Society in November, 1804. He served as its Recording Secretary from 1805 to 1819, as its Librarian, 1810-1811, and as Treasurer, 1819-1827. His other social and cultural activities included serving as trustee of the New York Society Library, Senior Warden and then Master of Holland Lodge, Free and Accepted Masons. He also served as sagamore of the Tammany Society, which funded the American Museum, initially a single room exhibit space in old City Hall. John Pintard served as a trustee and secretary of the museum, which was sold from John Scudder to P.T. Barnum in 1841 and became Barnum's American Museum. Pintard was also actively involved in the American Academy of Fine Arts, the Chamber of Commerce, Sailors' Snug Harbor, free schools and Sunday schools, the American Bible Society, the Erie Canal, the first Bank for Savings in New York, the Episcopal Church, particularly the old French Huguenot Church of St. Esprit, and the General Theological Seminary.
His sons died in youth, and his elder daughter Eliza Noel married, in 1810, a Kentuckian, Richard Davidson, and lived in Pinckneyville, Mississippi Territory and then New Orleans. His younger daughter, Louise Hall Pintard, married, on April 4, 1824, Thomas L. Servoss (1786-1866), son of Jacob and Isabella Servoss of Philadelphia, a widower with one son, Thomas Courtney Servoss. The Servoss family moved to New York, with Thomas engaged as a merchant, and Mr. and Mrs. Pintard lived in their home. Pintard also had a cook named Tamar Felmetta for over a decade. Eliza died in 1833, and Mrs. Pintard died on October 13, 1838. John Pintard died in New York City, June 21, 1844, at the age of eighty-five. His remains were placed in the family vault under St. Clement's Church on Amity (West Third) Street, and were removed in June 1910, upon the demolition of the edifice, to St. Michael's Cemetery, Queens, NY.
Source: Pintard, J., & Barck, D.C. (1940). Letters from John Pintard to his daughter, Eliza Noel Pintard Davidson, 1816-1833. 4 Volumes. New York, Printed for the New-York Historical Society.
Scope and Content Note
The John Pintard Papers include the correspondence, financial and business records, legal records, journals, notes and ephemera of John Pintard and his family. John Pintard's correspondence, 1784-1842, deals with such matters as his business activities, his financial difficulties and bankruptcy in the 1790s, the election of 1812, politics throughout the period, family matters, death or illness of friends, and his interest in various academic, cultural, philanthropic, and religious organizations. Included in his diaries and journals is a detailed journal of his daily reading while in debtor's prison 1797-1798. The financial and business records of John Pintard include receipts, bills, and other documents pertaining to his personal and family finances and the finances of organizations he was active in, usually as secretary or treasurer, including the New-York Historical Society. The legal records of John Pintard include early evidences of proceedings undertaken toward bankruptcy protection soon after the law allowed it.
The Servoss Family Papers provide a thorough record of the domestic, mercantile, and institutional activities of John Pintard's daughter Louise's New York based family. The records cover mostly their immediate family and include the records of their children, and their childrens' adult activities and interests.
The records of Other Family and Associates includes materials created by individuals in the Pintard family or in the family's orbit. There are many family records pertaining to the generation prior to John Pintard, mainly those of his uncle Lewis Pintard. Frequently, there is correspondence between two or more of John Pintard's frequent correspondents.
Related Materials
The New-York Historical Society has in its manuscript collection the papers of William Duer (1747-1799), John Pintard's business partner in dealings that led to both men being imprisoned for debt in the 1790's.
The New-York Historical Society's New Orleans Collection includes records regarding the development of New Orleans in the early to mid nineteenth century contemporary with Pintard's writings and collection of data in New Orleans, and his daughter Eliza's residency there.
The New-York Historical Society has in its manuscript collection a single volume of DeWitt Clinton correspondence (1784-1828), as well as DeWitt Clinton's diaries (1777-1828). A frequent correspondent of John Pintard, Clinton served as Mayor of New York City (1803-1815) and Governor of New York State (1817-1822, 1825-1828), and worked closely with Pintard in the founding of the New-York Historical Society and the Erie Canal Commission.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Arrangement Note
The John Pintard Papers are arranged in three series:
Each of these series includes subseries by document type.
Missing Title
Series 1: Papers of John Pintard
Series II: Papers of the Servoss Family
Series III: Papers of Other Family and Associates
Invoices.; Ledgers (account books); Leases.; Manuscripts (documents); Account books.; Bankbooks.; Circular letters.; Drafts (documents); Ephemera.; Financial records.; New York (N.Y.); Correspondence.; Deeds.; Contracts.; Erie Canal (N.Y.).; Elections -- United States -- 1812.; Certificates.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; French spoliation claims.; Philanthropists.; Merchants.; New Orleans (La.); Debt, Imprisonment for -- United States.; United States -- Politics and government -- 19th century.; Diaries.; Transcripts.; Notes (documents); Newspapers.; American Academy of the Arts; American Bible Society; Bayard, Samuel, 1767-1840; Blackstone, William, 1723-1780 -- Blackstone's commentaries on the laws of England; Boudinot, Elias, 1740-1821.; Clinton, DeWitt, 1769-1828; Clinton, James Henry; Davidson family; Davidson, Eliza Noel Pintard, 1787-1833; Davidson, Richard; Francis, John W. (John Wakefield), 1789-1861; General Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.); Hall, Fitch; Jarvis, Samuel F. (Samuel Farmer), 1786-1851; Livingston, Walter, 1740-1797; New-York Historical Society; New York (N.Y.). Common Council; Pintard (Family); Pintard, John, 1759-1844.; Pintard, Lewis, 1732-1818; Serred, Jacob; Servoss, Louise Pintard; Servoss, Thomas L., 1786-1866; Servoss (Family)
- Series 1: Papers of John Pintard, 1779-1851
  Scope and Content Note
  The Papers of John Pintard include correspondence, financial and business records, legal records, journals, notes, ephemera and meeting minutes.
  John Pintard's correspondence, 1780-1840, deals with such matters as his business activities, his financial difficulties and bankruptcy in the 1790s, the election of 1812, politics throughout the period, family matters, death or illness of friends, and his interest in various academic, cultural, philanthropic, and religious organizations.
  The series contains journals kept by John Pintard at various times between 1783 and 1811. Included is a detailed journal of his daily reading while in debtor's prison 1797-1798, encompassing classical studies, the Greek Testament, legal, theological, and economic works, Dr. Johnson's Dictionary of the English Language item by item, contemporary English poetry and the plays of Shakespeare. There are only a few diary entries in his reading journal which refer to the actual conditions of life in prison. Also included are a journal of New York weather kept in 1779, and detailed observations from his 1801 trip to New Orleans.
  The financial and business records contain evidence of the economic activity of the Pintard family and the organizations in which John Pintard worked. The legal records include business and property concerns. The notes and ephemera are varied writings on many topics as well as fragmentary notes. The meeting minutes subseries includes the records taken of organizational meetings of groups that John Pintard was involved with. The genealogies are in Pintard's hand and sketch out his ancestral background.
  - Subseries I: Correspondence, 1784-1842
    The correspondence of John Pintard is arranged chronologically and according to whether it was sent or received by John Pintard.
    The correspondence of John Pintard to his daughter Eliza Noel Pintard Davidson is published in an edited and abridged four volume work:
    PINTARD, J., & BARCK, D. C. (1940). Letters from John Pintard to his daughter, Eliza Noel Pintard Davidson, 1816-1833. 4 Volumes. New York, Printed for the New-York Historical Society.
    Vol. 1 includes a General Introduction by editor Dorothy Barck and Vol. 4 includes a detailed index.
    This work is available digitally via the Internet Archive -
    vol. 1: http://www.archive.org/details/lettersfromjohnp701pint vol. 2: http://www.archive.org/details/lettersfromjohnp712pint vol. 3: http://www.archive.org/details/lettersfromjohnp723pint vol. 4: http://www.archive.org/details/lettersfromjohnp734pint
    Some of John Pintard's more frequent correspondents include John Wakefield Francis, Walter Livingston, DeWitt Clinton, James Henry Clinton (serving aboard U.S.S. Constellation), his son-in-law Dr. Richard Davidson of New Orleans and other members of the Davidson family, Samuel Bayard of Princeton (N.J.), Fitch Hall of Boston, Elias Boudinot, Samuel Farmar Jarvis, and his uncle Lewis Pintard. There is a large group of letters to his daughter, Eliza Noel Pintard (Mrs. Richard Davidson), of Pinckneyville, Mississippi Territory, and New Orleans, 1816-1833.
    The correspondence of John Pintard is arranged chronologically and according to being sent or received by John Pintard.
    Pintard, J., & Barck, D.C. (1940). Letters from John Pintard to his daughter, Eliza Noel Pintard Davidson, 1816-1833. 4 Volumes. New York, Printed for the New-York Historical Society.
    This work is available digitally via the Internet Archive
    Vol.1
    Vol.2
    Vol.3
    Vol.4
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1820 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1822 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1824 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1825 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1826 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1827 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1828 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1829 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1830 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1831 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1832 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Letters from John Pintard to Eliza Pintard Davidson, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Letters from John Pintard, 1784-1815 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Letters from John Pintard, 1816-1819 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Letters from John Pintard, 1820-1824 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Letters from John Pintard, 1825-1826 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Letters from John Pintard, 1827 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Letters from John Pintard, 1828-1829 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Letters from John Pintard, 1830-1831 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Letters from John Pintard, 1832-1833 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Letters from John Pintard, 1834-1842 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Letters to John Pintard, 1787-1808 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Letters to John Pintard, 1810-1815 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Letters to John Pintard, 1816-1819 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Letters to John Pintard, 1820-1824 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Letters to John Pintard, 1825-26 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Letters to John Pintard, 1827 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Letters to John Pintard, 1828-1829 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Letters to John Pintard, 1830-1835 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Letters to John Pintard, 1836-1841 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Letters to John Pintard, Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Photostats and Transcripts, Undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Subseries II: Diaries and Journals, 1779-1811
    This subseries contains diaries and journals kept by John Pintard at various times between 1783 and 1811. Included is a detailed journal of his daily reading while in debtor's prison 1797-1798, encompassing classical studies, the Greek Testament, legal, theological, and economic works, Dr. Johnson's Dictionary of the English Language item by item, contemporary English poetry and the plays of Shakespeare. There are only a few diary entries in his reading journal which refer to the actual conditions of lilfe in prison. Also included are a journal of New York weather kept in 1779, and detailed observations from his 1801 trip to New Orleans. In some cases, transcripts and photostats of the journals are available.
    - Diary of the Weather, New York City, 1779 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Diary and Garden Calendar, 1793-1794 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Diary and Garden Calendar (Transcript), Undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Diary: Newark, 1793-1794 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Diary: Newark (Transcript), Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Prison Reading Diary, 1797-1798 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Prison Reading Diary (Transcript), Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Journal of Studies, 1797-1804 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Existence and Location of Copies
      Digital copy of Journal of Studies is available in the Shelby White and Leon Levy Digital Library.
    - Diary, 1798-1801 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Diary (Handwritten Copy), 1798-1801 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Diary, July-August 1800 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Diary, 1800-1801 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Diary (Transcripts), Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Diary of Visit to Washington (Transcript), Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Diary, 1806-1811 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Journal: Essays on Various Subjects (vol. 1), 1806-1809 (Volume 1)
    - Journal: Essays on Various Subjects (vol. 2), 1806-1809 (Volume 2)
    - Manuscript Bible (vol. 3), Undated (Volume 3)
    - Bible Presented to John Pintard by the American Bible Society (vol. 4), 1832 (Volume 4)
  - Subseries III: Financial and Business Records, 1782-1840
    The financial and business records of John Pintard include receipts, bills, and other documents pertaining to his personal and family finances and the finances of organizations he was active in, usually as secretary or treasurer, including the New-York Historical Society. Also included are promissory notes and other records relevant to John Pintard's business dealings with William Duer, both of whom were put in debtor's prison in the 1790's.
    Also included are accounts of exports out of the port of New York in the 1770's, a list of all ships entering the port of New Orleans and their cargo in 1800, and a list of parishoners payments for reserving pews at the St. Esprit French Protestant Chruch in New York.
    - Financial and Business Records, 1782-1834 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Financial and Business Records, Undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Shipping Log, 1792 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Account Book: Academy of the Arts, 1816-1817 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Account Book: Personal, 1836-1840 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - New-York Historical Society Business Records, 1805-1820 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - New-York Historical Society Business Records, 1821-1857 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Financial and Business Records (Oversize), 1798-1800 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Subseries IV: Legal Records, 1793-1836
    The legal records of John Pintard include early evidences of proceedings undertaken toward bankruptcy protection soon after the law allowed it, legal records relevant to his activity as a merchant, and New York City regulations signed by Pintard in his capacity as City Inspector.
    - Legal Records, 1793-1836 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Legal Records (Oversize), 1807-1836 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Subseries V: Notes and Ephemera
    This subseries includes various writings on many topics such as genealogy, politics, current events, history, religion, etc. It also includes newspaper clippings, certificates, and addresses.
    - Handwritten Notes, circa 1770-1840 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
      The Notes and Ephemera subseries contains written matter and newspaper clippings. Included are many notes taken by Pintard based on his reading, such as lists of books and authors. Also included are many brief writings on various topics. The newspaper clippings are relevant to his interests and concerns.
    - Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Memoir on the Trade in New Orleans, 1817 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Certificates and Addresses, 1809-1829 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Notes, Reminiscenes, 1841 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Reminiscences of the Early Life of John Pintard, 1841 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Reminiscences of the Early Life of John Pintard (Partial Transcript), Undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper Clippings, circa 1770-1840 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Notes and Ephemera (Oversize), 1839, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Subseries VI: Meeting Minutes
    This subseries includes records of the topics covered during organized meetings of charitable, cultural, and civic groups that John Pintard held membership in.
    - Index of Meeting Minutes, NYC Common Council, 1790-1793 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Index of Meeting Minutes, NYC Common Council, 1803-1806 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Meeting Minutes, circa 1770-1820 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Subseries VII: Genealogies
    The genealogies subseries contains genealogical charts and lists drawn up by John Pintard.
    - Genealogies, 1822, 1831, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Series II: Papers of the Servoss Family, 1806-1925
  The Servoss family papers include the records of the family of John Pintard's daughter Louise. Louise Hall Pintard, married, on April 4, 1824, Thomas L. Servoss (1786-1866) son of Jacob and Isabella Servoss of Philadelphia, a widower with one son. The Servoss family moved to New York, with Thomas engaged as a merchant, and Mr. and Mrs. Pintard lived in their home. Their children included Elias Boudinot Servoss.
  - Subseries I: Correspondence, 1806-1896
    - Letters to and from the Servoss family, 1806-1830 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Letters to and from the Servoss family, 1832 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Letters to and from the Servoss family, 1833-1847 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Letters to and from the Servoss family, 1848-1856 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Letters to and from the Servoss family, 1857-1859 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Letters to and from the Servoss family, 1860-1863 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Letters to and from the Servoss family, 1864 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Letters to and from the Servoss family, 1865-1869 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Letters to and from the Servoss family, 1870-1879 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Letters to and from the Servoss family, 1881-1896 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Subseries II: Financial and Business Records
    The financial and business records of the Servoss family document their business and domestic finances, including receipts, bills, ledgers, and memo books.
    - Servoss Market Book, 1809-1826 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Servoss Account and Receipt Books, 1811-1854 (Box 10, Folder 4)